Guide to the Papers of Richard Varick 1743-1871 (Bulk 1775-1830) MS 655
New-York Historical Society
Richard Varick Papers
1743-1871 (bulk 1775-1830)
New-York Historical Society
MS 655
2.5 Linear feet (5 boxes)
Richard Varick, born in New Jersey, 1753, served as Captain, deputy muster-master-general, and George Washington's secretary during the Revolutionary war. He was appointed one of the first mayors of New York and served from 1789-1801. He died in 1831. His papers contain items resulting from his military, legal, and political careers, as well as personal and familial correspondence and accounts--including letters received, drafts of letters sent, accounts, receipts, military orders, inventories, muster and pay rolls, military pay accounts, indentures, court-martial papers and civil court papers. The Richard Varick papers are digitized and available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Biographical Note
Missing Title
1753 Mar. 23 Born in Hackensack, NJ. Son of John Varick.
1775 Captain in Alexander McDougall's regiment
1775 July 1 Appointment by General Phillip Schuyler as his secretary
1776 Sept. 25 Appointed by Congress as Deputy muster-master-general
1777 Apr. 10 Lieutenant-colonel
1780 Inspector-general at West Point, and first aide-de-camp to General Benedict Arnold
1781 Recording secretary for General Washington
1784-1789 Recorder of New York City
1787-1788 Speaker of the New York State Assembly
1787-1816 Trustee of Columbia College
1788-1789 Attorney-general of the State of New York
1789 Varick and Samuel Jones appointed revisers of New York States laws (codified state statutes)
1789-1801 Mayor of New York
[1803]-1820 President of Merchants Bank
1816-1831 Founder and benefactor of American Bible Society
1828-1831 President of American Bible Society
1831 July 30 Died in Jersey City, NJ
Richard Varick was married to Maria Roosevelt, daughter of Isaac Roosevelt who was the son of James Roosevelt.
Scope and Content Note
This collection of Richard Varick's papers contains items resulting from his military, legal, and political careers, as well as personal and family papers such as correspondence and accounts. The majority of the collection dates from the Revolutionary War, and over half of the collection consists of correspondence.
The collection includes letters received, drafts of letters sent, accounts, receipts, military orders, inventories, muster and pay rolls, military pay accounts, indentures, court-martial papers and civil court papers. Also contained within the collection are papers about veterans' claims to military lands in New York State, including some maps; papers relating to the settlement of the estate of Derick Dey, Varick's maternal grandfather, and the affairs of other members of the Dey family; personal and family correspondence and accounts; and a few documents signed by Varick in his capacity as mayor of New York.
The papers in the collection pertain to a variety of subjects, including Varick's command of a company in Alexander McDougall's battalion at Ticonderoga and in Canada during 1775; his service on courts-martial in 1775; problems of the bateau service in northern New York State in 1776; his position as secretary to Gen. Philip Schuyler in 1775-1776; his work as deputy muster master general, inspector general at West Point, first aide-de-camp to Benedict Arnold (including papers about Arnold's defection and subsequent investigations), and as recording secretary for George Washington (including papers about the transcription of Washington's letters); and suits handled by him as an attorney practicing in Poughkeepsie in 1782-1783, and in New York City after the war.
Arrangement
The Richard Varick Papers have been arranged into the following six series.
The materials within each folder are arranged chronologically.
Missing Title
Series I. Correspondence
Series II. Military Documents
Series III. Legal Documents
Series IV. Accounts, Bills, Receipts
Series V. Appointments to Various Offices
Series VI. Genealogies
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
See Richard Varick Papers, 1775-1806 shelved at BV Varick.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital copies are available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
Correspondence.; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783.; Dey, Derick -- Estate; United States. Continental Army -- Pay, allowances, etc.; Courts-martial and courts of inquiry; Land grants -- New York (State); Mayors -- New York (State) -- New York; New York (State) -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; Accounts; Receipts; Orders (military records); Inventories; Muster Rolls; Arnold, Benedict, 1741-1801; Bradford, William, 1755-1795; Carthy, Daniel; Cuyler, Cornelius; Day family; De Witt, Simeon, 1756-1834; Dey, Derick --Estate; Elting, Peter; Gano, Daniel, 1758-1849; Gates, Horatio, 1728-1806; Glen, Henry, 1739-1814; Lamb, John, 1735-1800; Lansing, Jacob John; Lansing, John, 1754-1829; Laurance, John, 1750-1810; Lush, Richard; Romeyn, Dirck; Rutgers, Henry, 1745-1830; Sanders, John, 1756-1841; Schuyler, Philip John, 1733-1804; Schuyler, Phillip John, --1733-1804; Scott, John Morin, 1730-1784; Sewell, Henry, 1753-1845; Trumbull, Jonathan, 1740-1809; Van Rensselaer, Philip, 1747-1798; Varick family; Varick, John V.B.; Varick, John; Varick, Richard; Visscher, Matthew; Ward, Joseph, 1737-1812; Washington, George, --1732-1799; Woodruff, Lewis, 1754-1816; Yates, Peter W. (Peter Waldron)
- Series I: Correspondence
  Scope and Contents note
  This series, making up over half of the collection, contains correspondence received by or written by Varick. Some of his more frequent correspondents were: Lt. Daniel Gano, Cornelius Cuyler, Philip John Schuyler, Gen. Horatio Gates, Col. Joseph Ward, James Lamb, John Varick, Jr., Richard Lush, John Lansing, Jr., Henry Rutgers, Jr., Jacob John Lansing, Henry Sewall, Lewis Woodruff, William Bradford, Jr., John Morin Scott, Daniel Carthy, Dirck Romeyn, Henry Glen, Matthew Visscher, Peter W. Yates, John Laurance, Peter Elting, Philip Van Rensselaer, Col. Jonathan Trumbull, John V.B. Varick, John Sanders, and Simeon De Witt.
  - Subseries 1: Letters received.
    This subseries contains letters written to Varick. It begins with letters where the author of the letter could not be indentified. Following are single letters or small groups of letters that are alphabetized by author. Following these, each folder is dedicated to one author, and each contains four or more letters. These are alphabetized by last name.
    - unidentified correspondents, 1776-1798 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - A - B, single letters or small groups, 1779-1830 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - C, single letters or small groups, 1775-1821 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - D - F, single letters or small groups, 1776-1804 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - G, single letters or small groups, 1776-1791 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - H, single letters or small groups, 1776-1794 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - J - L, single letters or small groups, 1776-1798 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - M - O, single letters or small groups, 1776-1798 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - P - R, single letters or small groups, 1776-1821 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - S, single letters or small groups, 1776-1825 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - T, single letters or small groups, 1779-1798 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - V - Z, single letters or small groups, 1776-1821 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - French correspondents written in French, 1793-1811 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Theodorus Bailey, 1784-1787 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - William Bradford, 1778-1779 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Daniel Carthy, 1780 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - [Capt. W.] Colfax, 1781-1782 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Cornelius Cuyler, 1776 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Simeon DeWitt, 1797, 1814-1815 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Dey Family, 1780-1781, 1821 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - James Duane, 1784-1789 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Peter Elting, 1776-1783 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Daniel Gano, 1775-1778 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - [Major C.] Gibbs, 1780 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Nic Gilman, 1780 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Oliver Glean, 1781-1783 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Henry Glen, 1776-1783 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Frank Green, 1779 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - John Hancock, 1821 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Udney Hay, 1775-1784 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Hugh Hughes, 1781-1782 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Charles Knight, 1782-1791 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - James Lamb, 1777-1780 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Jacob J. Lansing, 1770-1771 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - John Lansing, 1776-1777 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - John Lansing, 1778-1783 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - John Laurance, 1782-1783 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Henry B. Livingston, 1776-1782 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Zach Lukels, 1781-1783 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Richard Lush, 1777-1782 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Alexander McDougall, 1775-1782 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - James Morrell, 1782-1783 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Isaac Nicoll, 1778-1789 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Dirck Romeyn, 1780-1782 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Isaac Roosevelt, 1788 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Henry Rutgers, 1778-1779 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Phillip John Schuyler, 1776-1796 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - John Morin Scott, 1775-1784 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Henry Sewell, 1770-1781 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Jonathan Trumbull, 1781-1794 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Pierre Van Cortlandt, 1783-1796 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Peter L. Van Rensselaer, 1779-1783 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Varick family, 1776-1782 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Matthew Visscher, 1781-1783 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Joseph Ward, 1777-1780 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Peter Wilson, 1778-1785 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - [W.] Wilson, 1801 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Lewis Woodruff, 1778-1779 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Anna [Yale], 1776-1777 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Peter Yates, 1781-1790 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 2: Drafts and copies of letters sent
    This subseries contains drafts and copies of letters written by Varick. It begins with letters where the intended recipient could not be indentified. Following are single letters or small groups of letters that are alphabetized by recipient. Following these, each folder is dedicated to one recipient, and each contains four or more letters. These are alphabetized by last name.
    - Unidentified correspondents, 1776-1779 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - A - C, single letters or small groups, 1776-1819 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - D - F, single letters or small groups, 1776-1780 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - G - H, single letters or small groups, 1776-1780 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - J - L, single letters or small groups, 1775-1823 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - M - P, single letters or small groups, 1776-1782 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - R - T, single letters or small groups, 1776-1805 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - V - W, single letters or small groups, 1776-1826 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - William Bradford, 1778-1779 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Continental Congress, 1777-1783 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - James Duane, 1777-1780 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Daniel Gano, 1775-1776 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Horatio Gates, 1776-1801 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - John Hancock, 1776-1777 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - [Gen.] Heath, 1780 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Alexander McDougall, 1776-1777 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Timothy Pickering, 1779 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Phillip Schuyler, 1776-1780 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Phillip L. Van Rensselaer, 1778-1829 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Abraham Van Vechten, 1810-1819 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - John Varick, 1825-1830 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Joseph Ward, 1777-1778 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - George Washington, 1776 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Subseries 3: Other correspondence
    This subseries contains correspondence that is neither from nor to Varick, several invitations and RSVPs, and documents that list the contents of Varick's books of transcribed letters.
    - Other correspondents, 1775-1801 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Invitations and RSVPs, 1786-1821 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - "Contents of books/letters transcribed", 1781 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Series II: Military Documents
  This series contains documents that pertain to Varick's position as deputy muster master general and his service on courts-martial trials. Also included are various military orders and memoranda and several inventories that detail Captain Varick's clothing and possessions during his military service.
  - Muster rolls, payrolls, billeting rolls, military pay accounts, 1775-1782 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Military orders and memoranda, 1775-1783 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Court martials (proceedings, prisoners reports, orders), 1775-1776 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Inventories of Captain Varick's military clothing and goods, 1776-1778 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Series III: Legal Documents
  This series contains a variety of legal documents arising from Varick's military, legal, and political careers--including court papers; and documents from the investigation into Varick after Benedict Arnold's defection. The series also contains documents regarding his personal and family estate--including papers relating to the settlement of the estate of Derick Dey, Varick's maternal grandfather; the affairs of other members of the Dey family; and indentures, bonds, deeds, and mortgages held by Varick.
  - Papers relating to the estate of Derick Dey and the affairs of other members of the Dey family, 1743-1761 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Papers relating to the estate of Derick Dey and the affairs of other members of the Dey family, 1762-1850 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Last wills and testaments of Richard Varick, 1775, 1795, 1831 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Last wills and testaments of Richard Van Varick and Abraham Varick, 1782, 1813 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Congressional resolutions, 1776-1777 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Documents from the Court of Inquiry for Varick's involvement with Benedict Arnold (deposition, affidavit, declaration), 1780 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Papers about veterans' claims to military lands in New York State, including some maps, 1784-1815 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - State Supreme Court of NY papers, 1785-1805 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Chancery case file with members of the Ludlow family as plaintiffs (large bound doc), 1810 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Indentures, bonds, deeds, mortgages, 1817-1832 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Other legal documents, [1786-1833] (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Series IV: Accounts, Bills, Receipts
  This series contains a multitude of bills, receipts and accounts, the majority dating from and relating to Varick's time in military service during the Revolutionary War. In addition, there are a number of bills and receipts from New York tradesmen for property repairs.
  - Accounts, 1775-1783 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Accounts, 1786-1830 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Receipts (mainly for provisions or pay received), 1775-1823 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Bills and receipts for work and equipment (mainly for property repairs) supplied by New York tradesmen, 1803-1808 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - US Internal Revenue income tax form for Abe Varick, 1871 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Series V: Appointments to Various Offices
  This series contains documents that recognize Varick's appointments to various offices of honor, including his commission as Captain and his appointments as Mayor of New York.
  - Commission as Captain, 1776 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Appointment as solicitor and counselor at law for New Jersey, 1779 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Appointments as mayor of New York (one including large wax seal), 1790, 1794 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Letter signifying election as director of Bank of New York, 1794 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Acceptance letter of his resignation as President of the Merchant Bank of New York and praise of his service, 1820 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Series VI: Genealogies
  This series contains one item, a genealogy of the Berthoff and Varick families.
  - Genealogy of Berthoff and Varick families, 1780 (Box 5, Folder 11)